{"tossups": [{"question": "Similarities of this speech to Abraham Lincoln\u2019s Gettysburg Address have been noted by scholars, as both praise \"the uniqueness of the State\u2019s commitment to democracy.\u201d The speaker of this address proclaims, \u201cThus choosing to die resisting, rather than to live submitting, they fled only from dishonor\u201d when referring to a certain group of people. This speech was recorded by Thucydides in his book <em>History of the Peloponnesian War</em>. For ten points, what \"Oration\" was spoken by an Athenian politician to honor the soldiers who perished fighting the Spartans?", "answer": "<b><u>Pericles\u2019s Funeral</u></b> Oration (accept equivalents)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A leader with this surname was deposed in Operation Fair Play, a coup led by Muhammad Zia-ul-Haq. Following a separatist movement led by Sheikh Mujib, a leader with this surname founded the PPP, or People's Party. A prime minister with this surname was killed in a car bombing in Rawalpindi in 2007. With Indira Gandhi, a prime minister with this surname signed the Shimla Agreement, which established the Line of Control in Kashmir. For ten points, identify this surname shared by Pakistani prime ministers Benazir and Zulfikar Ali.", "answer": "<b><u>Bhutto</u></b> (accept Benazir <b><u>Bhutto</u></b>; or Zulfikar Ali <b><u>Bhutto</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This attorney charged that Reuben Crandall's publications instigated slaves to rebel in the leadup to the Snow Riot. Earlier, this man prosecuted Richard Lawrence, who tried to use two malfunctioning firearms to kill Andrew Jackson. This man was detained aboard the HMS <em>Tonnant</em> to negotiate the release of William Beanes, during which time he wrote a poem that mentions \"the shore dimly seen through the mists of the deep.\" For ten points, name this lawyer, who wrote a poem about the shelling of Fort McHenry which later became \"The Star-Spangled Banner.\"", "answer": "Francis Scott <b><u>Key</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1665, public celebrations of this observance were banned under the Mughal emperor Aurangzeb. Guru Gobind Singh extended this observance for Sikhs, adding a three-day-long festival which traditionally includes martial arts demonstrations. In 2016, Pakistan controversially gave localities the power to declare this festival a public holiday. For ten points, name this Hindu \u201cFestival of Love\" that celebrates the arrival of spring and which is often celebrated by people throwing brightly colored powders.", "answer": "<b><u>Holi</u></b> (accept <b><u>Holi</u></b>ka Dahan; or Rangwali <b><u>Holi</u></b>; or <b><u>Dol Purnima</u></b>; or <b><u>Dhuleti</u></b>; or <b><u>Dhulandi</u></b>; or <b><u>Ukuli</u></b>; or <b><u>Manjal Kuli</u></b>; or <b><u>Yaosang</u></b>; or <b><u>Shigmo</u></b>; or <b><u>Phagwah</u></b>; or <b><u>Jajiri</u></b>; prompt on \"Festival of Spring\", \"Festival of Love\", or \"Festival of Colors\" before \"For ten points\")", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This politician was depicted as the \"after\" photo in a cover by the <em>Private Eye</em> with the headline, \u201cWorld\u2019s First Face Transplant A Success.\u2019\u201d This politician was heavily criticized after labeling another party as \u201cfruitcakes, loonies, and closet racists.\u201d The decision for the United Kingdom to opt out of the European Union led to this politician\u2019s resignation in 2016. For ten points, what Conservative politician preceded Theresa May as prime minister of the United Kingdom?", "answer": "David <b><u>Cameron</u></b> (or David William Donald <b><u>Cameron</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Despite originally being this man's campaign manager, James Garfield jumped him and James G. Blaine as the Republican presidential candidate in 1880. Accusations of bribery led to the belief that this man committed the \"Crime of '73.\" Due to the ineffective Valentine Act in his home state, this man supported a namesake act that involved a certain \"restraint of trade.\" Henry Clayton amended that act named for this Ohio senator, which permits \"innocent monopolies.\" For ten points, identify this namesake of an 1890 Antitrust Act.", "answer": "John <b><u>Sherman</u></b> (accept <b><u>Sherman</u></b> Antitrust Act of 1890)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The writing on the Pashupati seal found at this site has yet to be deciphered. This site's initial excavation was led by Ernest Mackay, who discovered artworks including the soapstone \"Priest-King'' statue and the bronze \"Dancing Girl\" statuette. This site's Great Granary and Great Bath date from the Third millennium BCE, and this site's name means \"mound of the dead men'' in Sindhi. For ten points, name this archeological site in present-day Pakistan, a major center of the Indus Valley Civilization.", "answer": "<b><u>Mohenjo-daro</u></b> (prompt on \"Indus Valley\" or \"Indus Valley Civilization\" before mentioned; prompt on \"Sindh\" before \"Sindhi\"; prompt on \"Pakistan\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Signs protesting this event encouraged residents to \u201cbuy no milk.\u201d An editorial by the <em>New York Times</em> dubbed this event the \u201cNightmare in the Catskills.\u201d Governor Nelson Rockefeller, who declared this event a \u201cdisaster zone,\u201d considered sending in the National Guard but was dissuaded by this event\u2019s organizer, John P. Roberts. Carlos Santana, the Killers, and Miley Cyrus were scheduled to perform in a failed revival of this event. For ten points, what landmark 1960s musical festival was held in Bethel, New York?", "answer": "<b><u>Woodstock</u></b> (or <b><u>Woodstock</u></b> Music and Art Fair; or <b><u>Woodstock</u></b> Rock Festival)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man, who founded and led the National Union of Mineworkers in the 1980s, was implicated in the violent Marikana massacre against striking miners. This Soweto-born politician lost a 1997 presidential election to fellow party member Thabo Mbeki [[mm-BEH-kee]]. In July 2021, this politician deployed the National Guard to the states of Gauteng and KwaZulu-Natal after the arrest of his predecessor, Jacob Zuma, caused riots and looting. For ten points, name this ANC politician and president of South Africa.", "answer": "Cyril <b><u>Ramaphosa</u></b> (or Matamela Cyril <b><u>Ramaphosa</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This state's Nutty Putty Cave was permanently filled in with concrete after John Jones became fatally stuck upside down in a narrow passageway in 2009. 19th century French fur trapper \u00c9tienne Provost inspired the name of a city in this state after he followed the Green River to discover this state's largest body of water. One National Park in this state was first homesteaded by Ebenezer Bryce. For ten points, name this western state where in 1928, Bryce Canyon National Park was established, one year before Arches National Park came into being.", "answer": "<b><u>Utah</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "At this location's Mormon Row, a structure built by T.A. Moulton has been called \"the most photographed barn in America.\" Menor's Ferry traversed the Snake River in this area, which became a National Park in 1929. Once known as the JY Ranch, the Laurance S. Rockefeller Preserve is located on the southern end of Phelps Lake in this park. For ten points, name this National Park in northwestern Wyoming, located just south of Yellowstone.", "answer": "<b><u>Grand Teton</u></b> National Park (accept <b><u>Grand Teton</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "An organization comprised of members of this ethnic group was infiltrated by Pinkerton detectives hired by Franklin B. Gowen, and a group known as the AOH advocated for this ethnic group\u2019s rights in Pennsylvania coal mines. Many members of that group, the Ancient Order of Hibernians, also belonged to a secret society of this ethnic group which was infiltrated by James McParland of the Pinkertons. The Molly Maguires were composed of, for ten points, what ethnic group that immigrated to the U.S. in massive numbers following an 1840s potato famine?", "answer": "<b><u>Irish</u></b>-Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Nubian soldiers headquartered near this city\u2019s Thika Road may have been the earliest inhabitants of one of its regions that began as a forest settlement. George Whitehouse originally founded this city that served as a depot during the construction of the Uganda Railway. In 2009, a rehousing scheme that was supported by Raila Odinga aimed to clear slums of this city, such as Kibera. In 1950, the East African Trade Unions Congress held a nine-day general strike in this city. For ten points, name this city shared by the Maasai and Kikuyu, the largest city and capital of Kenya.", "answer": "<b><u>Nairobi</u></b> (accept Enkare <b><u>Nairobi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One politician in this country often ended campaign speeches by stating, \u201cI\u2019m different.\u201d A 62-year-old wife of a former president of this country was the frontrunner and eventual winner of this country\u2019s 2021 general election. That woman, Xiomara Castro, is married to this country's former president, Manuel Zelaya. San Pedro Sula was one of the cities heavily affected by a 1998 Category 5 storm that hit this country, Hurricane Mitch. For ten points, name this Central American country that fought the 1960 Soccer War with neighboring El Salvador.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Honduras</u></b> (accept Rep\u00fablica de <b><u>Honduras</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In one speech, this man asked \u201cWhat is the mood of America and of the world toward America today?\u201d A campaign to go \u201cClean For [this man]\" involved the mass-shaving of beards among his supporters. Due to his anti-Vietnam War stance, this politician surged in the polls following the 1968 Tet Offensive. Like the eventual nominee from his party in that year, this man hailed from Minnesota. For ten points, name this Democrat who lost out to LBJ's preferred candidate, Hubert Humphrey, in the contentious 1968 Democratic National Convention.", "answer": "Eugene <b><u>McCarthy</u></b> (or Eugene Joseph \"Gene\" <b><u>McCarthy</u></b>; prompt on \"Go Clean for Gene\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A set of fortifications along a shore named for these people is detailed in the <em>Notitia</em> <em>Dignitatum</em>. These people faced a confederacy of Obotrites led by Drozko at the Battle of Bornh\u00f6ved. A group of these people who resided in Bayeux served in the army of Clovis I, and a pillar sacred to the pagan religion of these people was destroyed during the Massacre at Verden. Widukind was a leader of, for ten points, what Germanic group who settled England alongside the Angles?", "answer": "<b><u>Saxon</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Saxon</u></b>es; or <b><u>Sachsen</u></b>; or <b><u>Seaxan</u></b>; or <b><u>Sahson</u></b>; or <b><u>Sassen</u></b>; or <b><u>Saksen</u></b>; accept Anglo-<b><u>Saxon</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "One product created by this company was named after an inventor, because alleged attempts at \u201ceverything else\u2026 failed.\u201d That product was the Edison device, which was analyzed in a series of 2015 articles by John Carreyrou. In 2012, Safeway attempted to outfit its stores with products of this company that was founded by a nineteen-year-old who had dropped out of Stanford. SEC fraud charges were levelled against this company\u2019s founder, Elizabeth Holmes, who made exaggerated claims about its blood-testing products. For ten points, identify this healthcare technology company.", "answer": "<b><u>Theranos</u></b> (accept <b><u>Real-Time Cures</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "In a triptych named for this concept, the artist painted himself as a grayish figure helping a wounded man to the right of a figure floating above the scene. Figures such as Alekto, Pestilence, and Venus appear in a commentary painting by Peter Paul Rubens titled for the <em>Consequences of</em> [this concept]. In Vasily Vereshchagin's painting titled for <em>The</em> <em>Apotheosis of</em> [this concept], a pile of skulls sits outside the walls of a Central Asian city. For ten points, name this concept, depicted in a 1924 painting by Otto Dix inspired by his experiences in the trenches.", "answer": "<b><u>War</u></b> (accept <em>The</em> <em><b><u>War</u></b></em>; accept <em>The Apotheosis of</em> <em><b><u>War</u></b></em>; accept <em>Consequences of</em> <em><b><u>War</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This person and Thomas Pitt are depicted having a physical altercation in an</u></b> <b><u>illustration by James Gillray titled</u> </b><em><b><u>The Caneing in Conduit Street</u></b></em><b><u>. W. Kaye Lamb</u></b> <b><u>published an annotated edition of a manuscript detailing this explorer\u2019s voyages. (+)</u></b> <b>Puget [[PYOO-jet]] Sound, Mount Rainier, and Mount St. Helens were named by this explorer who departed England with the HMS </b><em><b>Chatham</b></em><b> and HMS (*) </b><em>Discovery</em>. For ten points, what British captain led expeditions to explore the Pacific and lends his name to a city in British Columbia?", "answer": "George <b><u>Vancouver</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An outlaw named Jack Black wrote a memoir about his experiences as one of</u></b> <b><u>these people titled</u> </b><em><b><u>You Can\u2019t Win</u></b></em><b><u>. These people often drew cats and triangles with</u></b> <b><u>hands among a series of crypto-signs used as part of their informal communication</u></b> <b><u>system. An ethical code (+)</u> of these people calls on them to take up the least desirable jobs possible in each new town. A willingness to engage in labor was historically seen as a contrast between these people and tramps. (*) </b>For ten points, name these migrant workers stereotypically depicted in media carrying their belongings in a bindle.", "answer": "<b><u>Hobo</u></b> (prompt on \u201ctramp\u201d before mentioned; prompt on \"migrant workers\"; prompt on \u201citinerant workers\"; prompt on \u201cvagabonds\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In her first major work, Hannah Arendt claimed that this agreement was \u201ca</u></b> <b><u>turning point in history\u201d since it led to the eschewing of historic customs as a \u201csource</u></b> <b><u>of law.\u201d This document calls for the creation of a \u201cpublic force\u2026instituted for the</u></b> <b><u>advantage of all\u201d and the (+)</u> sixth of its articles claims that \u201claw is the expression of the general will.\u201d Thomas Jefferson consulted on the initial drafts of this document written by the (*) </b>Marquis de Lafayette. For ten points, name this civil rights document penned during the French Revolution.", "answer": "Declaration of the <b><u>Rights of Man</u></b> and the Citizen (accept D\u00e9claration des <b><u>Droits</u></b> <b><u>de l'Homme</u></b> et du citoyen de 1789)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Wei Zheng wrote the</u> </b><em><b><u>Book of</u></b></em><b><u> [this dynasty], which included his own</u></b> <b><u>participation in Li Mi's Rebellion. During this dynasty, imperial architect Yuwen Kai</u></b> <b><u>[[KYE]] built Daxing [[DAH-SHING]] as an expansion of the Han capital of Xi'an [[ZHE-</u><u>AHN]]. (+)</u> A period known as \"The Southern and Northern Dynasties\" was ended after this dynasty's founder, Wen, conquered the Chen Dynasty south of the Yangtze. The (*) </b>Tang Dynasty succeeded, for ten points, what short-lived imperial dynasty which reunited China in the late 6th century?", "answer": "<b><u>Sui</u></b> Dynasty (or <b><u>Su\u00ed</u></b> ch\u00e1o)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A legend from the Mi\u2019kmaq states that this island was created by the \u201cGreat</u></b> <b><u>Spirit\u201d when he placed dark red clay in a crescent shape on pink water. Two</u></b> <b><u>privateers, Nicholson Broughton and John Selman, raided this island during the</u></b> <b><u>American (+)</u> Revolution. Opened in 1997, the Confederation Bridge connects this province to New Brunswick. The novel </b><em><b>Anne of </b></em><b>(*)</b><em>Green Gables</em> is set in, for ten points, what Canadian island province once part of Acadia?", "answer": "<b><u>Prince Edward</u></b> Island (or <b><u>PEI</u></b>; or \u00cele-du-<b><u>Prince-\u00c9douard</u></b>; accept <b><u>Minegoo</u></b>; or <b><u>Epekwitk</u></b>; accept <b><u>St. John\u2019s</u></b> Island or \u00cele <b><u>Saint-Jean</u></b>; prompt on \"Acadia\" before  mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man once infamously pointed a poker at Karl Popper's face, prompting</u></b> <b><u>the latter to describe that as breaking a \"moral rule.\" This thinker negated his own</u></b> <b><u>early work, and the entire Vienna Circle School, by developing the concept of</u></b> <b><u>\"language games\" (+)</u> in his second book, </b><em><b>Philosophical Investigations</b></em><b>. This man never returned to his native Austria following the Anschluss (*) </b>due to his Jewish ancestry. For ten points, name this student of Bertrand Russell, a transformative Analytic philosopher who wrote <em>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</em>.", "answer": "Ludwig <b><u>Wittgenstein</u></b> (or Ludwig Josef Johann <b><u>Wittgenstein</u></b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of this tribe\u2019s leaders feigned willingness to convert to Christianity in</u></b> <b><u>order to launch a surprise attack on English settlers. This tribe, once led by</u></b> <b><u>Opechancanough [[oh-puh-CHAN-kuh-noh]], established its main village at (+)</u></b> <b>Werowocomoco [[weh-roh-woh-KOH-moh-koh]], and its leaders were known as </b><em><b>mamanatowick</b></em><b>. One member of this tribe apocryphally saved John (*) </b>Smith from execution. Pocahontas was a member of, for ten points, what \"confederacy\" of Algonquin tribes from Eastern Virginia?", "answer": "<b><u>Powhatan</u></b> Confederacy (accept <b><u>Tsenacommacah</u></b>; accept <b><u>Attanoughkomouck</u></b>; prompt on \"Algonquin\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A character with this title who experiences peace during the \"Age of Gold\"</u></b> <b><u>despairs in Egypt over the sudden drowning of his lover. A character known as the</u></b> <b><u>\"arbiter of elegance\" owns a Christian slave girl in a novel set during the reign (+)</u> of a character with this title. Marguerite Yourcenar [[YOR-seh-nar]] wrote a novel titled the \"Memoirs\" of a person with this title, held by a character who loves the prostitute Calpurnia and hides behind a curtain. (*) </b>Robert Graves wrote a fictional biography of a character with, for ten points, what title held by Nero and Claudius?", "answer": "<b><u>Roman Emperor</u></b> (or <b><u>Emperor</u></b> of <b><u>Rome</u></b>; prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man formally apologized to Archbishop Christodoulos, the head of the</u></b> <b><u>Church of Greece, for offenses committed by Catholics against Orthodox populations</u></b> <b><u>during the Fourth Crusade. A Member of the ultra-nationalist Grey Wolves named (+)</u></b> <b>Mehmet Ali A\u011fca shot this figure during a procession in St. (*) </b>Peter's Square. The initiative World Youth Day was pioneered by, for ten points, what Polish-born pope who was succeeded by Pope Benedict XVI [[the Sixteenth]]?", "answer": "Pope <b><u>John Paul II</u></b> (or <b><u>JPII</u></b>; accept Karol J\u00f3zef <b><u>Wojty\u0142a</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}